之前在那些即将死去的人身上......
VESPASIAN: Previously
on Those About To Die...
谷物是故意拖延的，
PORTO: The grain was delayed
intentionally,
和谣言说弗拉维安
and rumors that a Flavian
-是粮食短缺的幕后推手.......弗拉维安人？
-was behind the food shortages.
-TITUS: A Flavian?
图密善，如果他成为皇帝，
ANTONIA: Domitian, were he
to become Emperor,
那将是我们所有人的终结。
that would be the end
of all of us.
是的！
Yes!
嗯，公民们，为罗马服务
Um, the citizens,
and to serve Rome
我将带来我们竞选活动的荣耀......
I will bring the glory
of our campaigns...
不 不 不。
No, no, no.
呃......嗯。
Um... Hmm.
正如我在遥远的战场上为罗马服务一样......不。
As I have served Rome
on distant battlefields... No.
是的，它是什么？
Yes, what is it?
也许，一个建议？
Perhaps, a suggestion?
是的，建议。
VESPASIAN: Yes, words.
说说你的建议，你善于言辞。
Give me the words.
You're good with words.
我。。。
I...
提图斯·弗拉维乌斯·维斯帕西亚努斯...
Titus Flavius Vespasianus...
我听不见。大声！
I can't hear you. Louder!
我。。。
I...
提图斯·弗拉维乌斯·维斯帕西亚努斯
Titus Flavius Vespasianus
戴上铁环。
wear an iron ring.
不是金子，
Not gold,
不是银，
not silver,
没有镶嵌宝石。
not encrusted
with precious stones.
铁，犁的东西，
Iron, the stuff of the plough,
还有短剑，
and the gladius,
还有骡子嘴里的那块
and the bit in the mouths
of the mules
我的父亲和祖父养育了。
my father and grandfather bred.
尼禄皇帝，贵族
Emperor Nero of late,
a patrician
八月家族，
of august family,
他戴着金子。
he wore gold.
他建造了金宫，
He built the Domus Aurea,
有史以来最宏伟的房子
the grandest house
ever to be built
在陆地上，他从他的公民那里偷走了。
on land he stole
from his citizens.
我，提图斯·弗拉维乌斯·维斯帕西亚努斯，
I, Titus Flavius Vespasianus,
将拆毁那个金宫
will tear down that Domus Aurea
-石头，用石头。
-stone, by stone.
-(VESPASIAN CHUCKLES)
取而代之的是，我将建造一个圆形剧场。
And in its place,
I shall build an amphitheater.
不是为了这个城市的主人，
Not for the masters
of this city,
而是为了娱乐和快乐
but for the entertainment
and pleasure
为众民。
of the citizenry.
铁人，他们的鲜血和辛劳
The men of iron
whose blood and toil
建造了这个，我们的罗马城。
built this, our city of Rome.
太不可思议了。
I am stunned.
想想我以为你的修辞老师
And to think I thought
your instructors in rhetoric
被多付了钱。
were overpaid.
而圆形剧场，是不是突然有了悟？
And the amphitheater,
was that a sudden insight?
不，我已经考虑了一段时间。
No, I've been considering it
for a while.
还有什么更好的方法来削弱马克西姆斯竞技场的力量
What better way to sap power
from the Circus Maximus
还有那些如此憎恨我们上升的贵族？
and the patricians
who so resent our ascent?
是的。
Yeah.
好吧，也许你已经指挥了我的一只翅膀。
Well, perhaps you already
command one of my wings.
政治的。
The political one.
这就是我想象中的样子。
DOMITIAN:
It's just how I imagined it.
浩瀚无垠，无以复加。
Vast beyond all comprehension.
尼禄从来不理解暴徒。
Nero never understood the mob.
他太专注于建造他愚蠢的金屋了
He was too focused on building
his stupid Golden House
拥有无尽的花园和水景，
with its endless gardens
and water features,
并弹奏他的七弦琴。
and playing his lyre.
我父亲在他一场乏味的音乐会上睡着了，
My father fell asleep
in one of his tedious concerts,
尼禄禁止他进入宫廷
and Nero banned him
from his court
并派他去犹太发动战争。
and sent him to wage war
in Judea.
最后，自杀是尼禄最后也是唯一的选择。
In the end, suicide
was Nero's last and only option.
他需要得到帮助。
And he needed
to be helped with that.
一个年轻的头脑发热的人。
A young hothead.
拜托了，伟大的图密善。
Please, Great Domitian.
明白他是单独行动的。
Understand he acted alone.
天哪，我迟到了。
By the gods, I'm late.
我什么时候能再见到你？
When can I see you again?
当我可以离开时。
When I can get away.
中午？傍晚？
Midday? Evening?
今晚？
Tonight?
我们在一起将近五个星期，
We are nearly
five weeks together,
而你能想到的就是做爱吗？
and all you can think of
is making love?
我呢？
Do I?
我必须告诉你一些事情。
I have to tell you something.
重要的事情。
Something important.
-告诉我，这是什么？
-Tell me, what is it?
-(SHUSHES)
今晚。
Tonight.
好。
Okay.
-去。-好。
-Go.
-Okay.
你喜欢哪一个？这个？
DRUSILLA: Which one
would you like? This one?
这个。
This one.
这是怎么回事，奥拉？
What's going on, Aura?
现在告诉我。
Now tell me.
我在那里。当那个人试图杀死你时，我就在那里。
I was there. I was there
when that man tried to kill you.
我知道有些不对劲。
And I knew something was wrong.
我就知道。我应该转过身来。
I knew it. And I should have
turned around.
我应该帮你的。
I should have helped you.
啊！埃利亚！欢迎回来。
ANDRIA: Ah! Elia! Welcome back.
你准备好了吗？
You ready to go?
Ferox 今天早上吃得好吗？
Did Ferox eat well this morning?
芹菜换血？
Celery for the blood?
我们在Baetica喂了它们。
We fed them back in Baetica.
现在我们在这里更好地喂养它们。
And now we feed them
even better here.
小兄弟，你不会迟到的。
It's not like you to be late,
little brother.
我睡过头了。
I overslept.
-在谁的床上？-他昨晚不在家？
-In whose bed?
-He wasn't home last night?
-今天早上也没有。-可以吗，
-Nor this morning.
-Can it be,
他发现的不仅仅是马，还有更多的生命？
he has discovered
more to life than horses?
来，让我们看看你是否已经成为一个男人。
Come, let's see
if you have become a man.
-西班牙人。-没什么可说的。
-A Spaniard.
-There is nothing to tell.
然而，你的束腰外衣走错了路。
Yet, your tunic is on
the wrong way.
-加油。
-Come on.
-(FONSOA CHUCKLES)
你认为我们的小爱情鸟独自过夜还是......
Do you think our little lovebird
spent the night alone or...
也许在一个舒适的巢穴里？嗯？
In a cozy nest, maybe? Hmm?
我看得出来，你不需要我的帮助。
I can see you are not
in need of my help.
-所以。。。-埃利亚。埃利亚。
-So...
-Elia. Elia.
我们为您感到高兴。
We are happy for you.
也许有一天我们能见到她。
Perhaps we can meet her one day.
我绝不会让她遭受这样的折磨。
(LAUGHS) Never would I
commit her to such an ordeal.
安德里亚，马匹准备好了。
Andria, the horses are ready.
安德里亚：今晚喝酒庆祝。
ANDRIA: Drinks tonight
to celebrate.
只是想说这都是一个可怕的错误。
Just meant to say
that this was all
a terrible mistake.
好吧，我可以向你保证没有人会听说它。
Well, I can assure you
no one will hear of it.
祝你好运。
Good luck out there.
今天是个好日子，不是吗？
Today's a good day, is it not?
游戏可能会让人有这种感觉。
The games
may make one feel such.
确实如此。越来越，甚至对我来说也是如此。
They do.
Increasingly, even for me.
还有更多的东西。
There's something more.
我，提图斯，
I, Titus,
凯撒·维斯帕西亚努斯，
Caesar Vespasianus,
给你今天的游戏
give you this day's games
关于建造公民浴场！
on building civic baths!
已经建设了两个月。
Already two months
under construction.
我宣布，我正在给我们心爱的罗马......
And I announce that I am
giving our beloved Rome...
继承人！
an heir!
他学得比我预期的要快。
He learns more quickly
than I expected.
嘿。
Hey.
要是我爸爸妈妈在这里看到就好了。
If only my mother and father
were here to see this.
整个罗马都在我的脚下。
All of Rome at my feet.
除非你赢了，否则不要叫。
Don't crow unless you win.
战车！
PASSUS: Chariots!
准备！
Ready!
耶！
Yah!
安德里亚的马在飞翔。
Andria's horses are flying.
给我赢点钱！
Win me some money! (LAUGHS)
谢天谢地，安德里亚领先于那个人。
Thank the Gods
Andria was ahead of that one.
方索阿，我需要你的帮助。
Fonsoa, I need your help.
来。
Coming.
安德里亚！安德里亚！安德里亚！
(CROWD CHANTING)
Andria! Andria! Andria!
耶！
Yah!
安德里亚！安德里亚！安德里亚！
(CHANTING)
Andria! Andria! Andria!
耶！
Yah!
天蝎座！
ANDRIA: Scorpus!
天蝎座，你在做什么？
Scorpus, what are you doing?
呀！耶！
SCORPUS: Yah! Yah!
天蝎座！
Scorpus!
安德里亚！
Andria!
来。
Come.
清空桌子！快 点！迅速！
GAVROS: Clear the table!
Hurry! Quickly!
加油。加油。
Come on. Come on.
我想见见她。
I would like to have met her.
你会的。
And you will.
永远是乐观主义者
Ever the optimist. (GASPING)
互相照顾。
Look after each other.
答应我。
Promise me.
我会告诉我们的母亲......
I will tell our mother...
我们伟大的冒险。
of our great adventure.
安德里亚。
ELIA: Andria.
Andria.
不！
No!
天蝎座！天蝎座！天蝎座！
CROWD: (CHANTING)
Scorpus! Scorpus! Scorpus!
你这个该死的渣滓！你杀了他！
You fucking scum!
You killed him!
他选择了自己的路线。
He chose his line.
不，是你！
No, it was you!
你拉到左边。
You pulled to the left.
告诉我你看到了什么。
Tell me what you saw.
他把安德里亚推到了残骸上。他把他关了进去。
He pushed Andria to the wreck.
He boxed him in.
够了。
TENAX: Enough of this.
再碰一下天蝎座，我就会得到你的头。
Touch Scorpus again,
and I will have your head.
我会因为杀死我的兄弟而得到你的。
And I will have yours
for killing my brother.
安德里亚死了。
Andria is dead.
这是个意外。
It was an accident.
结束了。
It's over.
我表示哀悼。
I offer my condolences.
多么悲惨的事故。
What a tragic accident.
-不。你撒谎！-我们的游戏很危险。
-No. You lie!
-Ours is a dangerous game.
你哥哥知道这一点。
Your brother knew that.
看看今天氙气发生了什么。
Look at what happened
to Xenon today.
他是对的，Elia。
He's right, Elia.
你不相信我。
You don't believe me.
我只是没有看到你说你看到了什么。
I just didn't see
what you say you saw.
他强迫安德里亚进入沉船，他把他装进了海里！
He forced Andria
into the shipwreck
He boxed him in!
-不。-你不能确定。
-No.
-You cannot be sure.
我不会再和你有任何关系了
I will have nothing more
to do with you
或者这个黄金派系。
or this Gold faction.
我有更多的马厩。
I have plenty more stablehands.
埃利亚。
Elia.
那不是天蝎座。那是一场沉船。
It wasn't Scorpus.
It was a shipwreck.
它发生了。
It happens.
你和他一样坏。
You are just as bad as he is.
你通常是一个比这更好的骗子。
You are usually
a better liar than that.
正如斯科普斯所说，
As Scorpus said,
还有其他的马厩，但只有一个天蝎座。
there are other stablehands,
but there's only one Scorpus.
我真傻。
Foolish of me.
我以为我在你身上看到了一丝体面。
I thought I had seen
a glimmer of decency in you.
而你呢，兄弟？你站在谁一边？
And you, brother?
On whose side are you on?
愿风带你去极乐世界，
GAVROS: May the winds
take you to Elysium,
众神会在哪里，
where the Gods will it,
我们会再见面的。
we'll meet again.
我从来没有时间或金钱为别人流下很多眼泪。
I never had the time or money
to shed many tears for others.
这就是你为残忍辩护的方式吗？
Is that how you justify cruelty?
我就是这样解释的。
That's how I explain it.
你可以对别人撒谎，
You can lie to others,
但是对自己撒谎是危险的。
but it's dangerous
to lie to yourself.
你不再是孩子了。
You are no longer a child.
你完全可以负担得起同情心的奢侈。
You can more than afford
the luxury of compassion.
旧习惯很难改变。
Old habits die hard.
这是道歉吗？
Is that an apology?
也许是这样。
Perhaps it is.
我不太关心你，想要你的道歉。
I don't care enough about you
to want your apology.
那些是需要它的人。
Those are the ones who need it.
我以为我们的安排是为了方便
I thought ours
was an arrangement
of convenience
让你帮助你的孩子。
to allow you
to help your children.
我不知道你会试图让我成为一个体面的人。
I didn't know you would try
to make me a decent man.
我不太在乎你的体面。
I don't care enough
about your decency.
或者缺乏它。
Or lack of it.
你小时候，我曾经在贝蒂斯河边追你。
I used to chase you
by the river Baetis
when you were young.
现在我又这样做了？
Now I do so again?
我们不再玩儿童游戏了。
We're no longer playing
children's games.
安德里亚最不希望看到的就是我们分裂了。
The last thing Andria
would have wanted
is that we are divided.
所以跟我来。
So come with me.
埃利亚！
Elia!
Elia，等等！
Elia, wait!
如果我和你一起走开，那么萨莱娜和那个男孩呢？
If I were to walk away with you,
what then of Salena and the boy?
这来自一个从未走过妓院的男人
This coming from the man
who has never walked past
a brothel
-口袋里有几枚硬币。-那是以前。
-with a few coins in his pocket.
-That was before.
-这就是现在。
-And this is now.
-(GRUNTS)
我不能背弃她。
I can't turn my back on her.
继续。还有什么？
Go on. What else?
Scorpus 和 Tenax 为我提供了黄金派系的第二位车手。
Scorpus and Tenax
offered me second driver
with the Gold Faction.
这个城市以这种方式扭曲了你
This city has twisted you
in such a way
你会和那些杀死我们兄弟的人一起开车。
that you would drive
with the men
who has killed our brother.
只有你一个人说。
Says you alone.
然后天蝎座从我身边带走了两个兄弟。
Then Scorpus has taken
two brothers from me.
埃利亚。
FONSOA: Elia.
所以
So,
他拒绝进食，也不想再打架了。
he refuses to eat
and he doesn't want to
fight anymore.
阿迪克斯： 他不想成为我们的傀儡。
ATTICUS: He doesn't want
to be our puppet.
现在多少周了？
How many weeks now?
快五点了，我的主。
Almost five, My Lord.
距离弗拉维安圆形剧场开放只有两周的时间。
And we only have
two weeks until
the Flavian Amphitheatre opens.
爱马 仕。
Hermes.
我们为您准备了一些美味佳肴。
We've prepared
some delicacies for you.
无花果。
Figs.
西班牙橄榄。
Spanish olives.
牡蛎。
Oysters.
在我的圆形剧场进行揭幕战时，你需要你的力量。
You'll need your strength
for the opening fight
at my amphitheater.
你应该感谢弗拉维乌斯·多米提亚努斯的恩惠。
You should thank
Flavius Domitianus
for his favor.
我们应该再试一次吗？
Should we try that again?
吃！你会战斗。
Eat! And you will fight.
试试那个。
Try with that one.
他们是朋友。
They're friends.
和他争吵的那个。
The one he spars with.
所以
So,
我们应该把箭射穿这个北方野蛮人的脖子吗？
should we put an arrow
through the neck
of this northern barbarian?
我感谢你的礼物。
I thank you for your gift.
弗拉维乌斯·多米提亚努斯。
Flavius Domitianus.
忠诚，无知者的愚蠢特质。你这条狗。
Loyalty, the dumb trait
of the ignorant. You dog.
好吧，现在我有最美味的
Well, now I have
the most delicious
和杀死那个的有趣方式。
and entertaining way
to kill that one.
特纳克斯：图密善喜欢表演。
TENAX: Domitian likes a show.
不是每天都有，我们要派遣参议员，甚至......
It's not every day, we get
to dispatch senators, even...
像这样奸诈的狗屎，不。
treacherous shits
like these, no.
他会想要一些特别的东西，一些戏剧性的东西。
He'll want something special,
something theatrical.
也许如果 Aedile Ludi 本人在这里，我们可以取悦他。
Perhaps if the Aedile Ludi
himself were here,
we could please him.
你可能是游戏的新主人，Tuccian，
You may be the new master
of the games, Tuccian,
但图密善让我成为 Aedile Ludi 的立法者。
but Domitian has made me
legislator of the Aedile Ludi.
不要质疑他的权威，也不要质疑我的权威。
Do not question his authority,
or mine.
答案是肯定的。原谅我。
Of course. Forgive me.
我理解你的保留意见。
I understand your reservations.
但相信我，
But trust me,
我在那些臭气熏天的摊位上长大。
I grew up in those
stinking stands.
我知道暴徒想看什么。
I know what the mob
wants to see.
我们需要招待他们。
We need to entertain them.
为了激发他们，为了......
To excite them, to...
让他们兴奋不已。
thrill them.
记住，够了就好了。
Remember, enough is good.
越多越好。
More is better.
太多了。。。
Too much...
是完美的。
is perfect.
淹没圆形剧场有多难？
How hard would it be
to flood the amphitheater?
这太慷慨了。
This is too generous.
为你的儿子接受它。
Accept it for your son.
如果不是为了你自己。
If not for yourself.
我还能用我所有的收入做什么？
What else am I going to do
with all my earnings?
我只能喝这么多酒。
I can only drink so much wine.
在一个条件下。
On one condition.
这是贷款，不是礼物。
This is a loan, not a gift.
当我重新获得我的股份时，我会还给你。
I will pay you back
when I regain my shares.
如果我重新获得我的股份。
If I regain my shares.
你会的。
You will.
事情会变得更好。
Things will get better.
方索阿，这是什么？
Fonsoa, what is it?
是我哥哥。
It's my brother.
我想念他。
I miss him.
如果Fonsoa是对的呢？
ELIA: What if Fonsoa is right?
如果这只是一个意外呢？
What if it was just an accident?
我，呃......
I, uh...
我没有好好看它。
I didn't have a good view of it.
你似乎是唯一一个这样做的人。
You seem to be
the only one who did.
氙！
Xenon!
他就在那里。他一定看到了什么。
He was right there.
He must have seen something.
天蝎座。
XENON: Scorpus.
我很抱歉，我的朋友。
I am so sorry, my friend.
你是？
Are you?
或者你只是来看看它是否真的是真的？
Or did you just come to see
if it's actually true?
那个氙气已经完成了。
That Xenon is finished.
废话。
Nonsense.
你和我很快就会再次比赛。
You and I will race again soon.
我，呃，带了礼物。
I've, uh, brought gifts.
因此，Atargatis可以减轻您的疼痛并加快您的康复速度。
So Atargatis can ease
your pain and speed up
your recovery.
这是怎麽？
What's this?
一份礼物。
A gift.
支付医生费用。
To pay for physicians.
任何你需要或想要的东西。
Anything you need or desire.
谢谢你，但我有足够的钱来支付我的医生费用。
Thank you,
but I have enough money
to pay for my physicians.
当然，我只是想减轻你的负担。
Of course, I seek only
to lighten your burden.
你认为几枚硬币能买到我的沉默吗？
Do you think a few coins
will buy my silence?
我不明白你。
I don't understand you.
是的，你有。
Yes, you do.
你强迫年轻的西班牙人进入脊柱。
You forced the young Spaniard
into the spina.
我看到了。
I saw it.
好吧，你错了。
Well, you are mistaken.
你受伤了。你的头脑不清楚。
You were injured.
Your mind was not clear.
不，天蝎座。
No, Scorpus.
我看到了我所看到的。
I saw what I saw.
你杀了那个男孩。
You killed that boy.
我坚持要你向派系所有者坦白。
And I insist that you confess
to the faction owners.
我不能那样做。
I cannot do that.
我会失去一切。我再也不会参加比赛了。
I would lose everything.
I would never race again.
请。
Please.
氙气，在那天晚上之后，
Xenon, after that evening,
我以为你和我现在是朋友了。
I thought you and I
were now friends.
带上你的友谊，
Take your friendship,
和你的礼物，
and your gift,
然后把它推到你的屁股上。
and shove it up your ass.
现在出去！
Now get out!
如果你不告诉他们，我会的。
XENON: (COUGHS)
If you don't tell them, I will.
氙。
Xenon.
医生在哪里？
Where is the physician?
他在哪？快点来。
Where is he? Come quickly.
他没有呼吸。
He's not breathing.
斯科普斯：这太可怕了。
SCORPUS: It's terrible thing.
氙
Xenon,
死了。
is dead.
这对我们所有人来说都是损失。
A loss for all of us.
你可能听说过。
GAVROS: You may have heard.
我们不再为黄金派系工作。
We no longer work
for the Gold Faction.
所以你找工作？
FIMBRIA: So you seek work?
是的。
GAVROS: Yes.
在罗马，没有人比我们更了解和驯服马匹。
No one in Rome knows
and tames horses
better than we do.
可悲的是，我们有一整套马厩和马夫。
Sadly, we have a full complement
of stablehands and grooms.
你误会我们了。
You misunderstand us.
我想参加比赛。
I wish to race.
-比赛？-是的。
-(SCOFFS) To race?
-Yes.
你是车夫吗？
Are you a charioteer?
我从来没见过你开车。
I've never seen you drive.
这是怎麽？
What is this?
这些绅士们是来做派系生意的。
These gentlemen
are here on faction business.
显然，任何与蓝色派系有关的事情都是我所关心的。
Clearly, and anything
that concerns the Blue Faction
is my concern.
这是加夫罗斯。
This is Gavros.
是的，我知道他是谁。
Yes, I know who he is.
这是埃利亚，死去的黄金司机的兄弟。
And this is Elia,
brother of the Gold driver
who died.
他还有另一个兄弟。仍在为金牌而战。
He has another brother.
Still driving for the Gold.
的确，罗穆卢斯和雷穆斯。
Indeed, Romulus and Remus.
他希望开车，但他没有受过训练，也没有经过验证。
He hopes to drive,
but he's untrained and unproven.
走近一点。
Come closer.
近。
Closer.
你哥哥为金牌开车。
Your brother drives
for the Gold.
你为什么要为蓝军而战？
Why would you race for the Blue?
因为天蝎座为黄金而开车。
Because Scorpus
drives for the Gold.
我会在赛道上面对他，
I will face him on the track,
我要打败他。
and I will defeat him.
你说他未经证实？
You said he's unproven?
是的。
FIMBRIA: Yes.
那么你必须证明自己。
Then you must prove yourself.
去我们的马厩装备。我今晚会在那里。
Go to our stables and rig up.
I'll be there this evening.
有数百名年轻人希望为蓝军开车。
FIMBRIA: There are hundreds
of young men wishing
to drive for the Blue.
为什么要给他机会？
Why give him a chance?
让他与众不同的一件事。
The one thing
that sets him apart.
他的仇恨。
His hatred.
你可以告诉我你想开车。
You could have told me
you wanted to drive.
有这么惊喜吗？
Was it such a surprise?
没有。
Not really.
但是，你还是应该告诉我的。
But still,
you should have told me.
马厩见。
See you at the stables.
我一直想见你。
I've been wanting to see you.
我听说过你哥哥。
I heard about your brother.
我的心在流血。
My heart bleeds.
任何人都无能为力。
There's nothing anyone can do.
我必须告诉你一些事情。
I have to tell you something.
我也需要告诉你一些事情。
And I need to tell you
something, too.
我要回家，去西班牙，去贝蒂卡。
I'm going back home,
to Spain, to Baetica.
-什么？-我必须先做点什么。
-What?
-I must do something first.
但只要我能，我就要离开了。
But as soon as I can,
I'm leaving.
对不起。
I'm sorry.
我的皇帝。
My Emperor.
波尔图告诉我，你有一个指控要提出。
Porto tells me
you have an accusation to make.
我只是有信息要传授，提图斯勋爵。
I merely have information
to impart, Lord Titus.
不要玩文字游戏。将其视为关于活动的现场报告。
Don't play with words.
Treat this like a field report
on campaign.
我相信你的兄弟图密善要为粮食延误负责。
I believe your brother Domitian
is responsible for
the grain delays.
还有食物骚乱。
And food riots.
提图斯：你有证据吗？
TITUS: Do you have proof?
其中一艘运粮船上的领航员，
A navigator
on one of the grain ships,
它在西西里岛海岸沉没，但他获救，然后被捕。
it sank off the coast of Sicily,
but he was rescued
and then arrested.
在我们发言时，证人正被押送到这里。
The witness is being
escorted here as we speak.
告诉我这些对你有什么好处？
And how does
telling me this benefit you?
我只想服侍你，服侍罗马。
I seek only to serve you
and serve Rome.
嗯。
Hmm.
我有很多客户，在参议院公开和秘密，
I have many clients,
open and secret
in the Senate,
足以影响任何投票。
enough to sway any vote.
我向你们提供全面和持续的支持
I offer you full
and sustained support
用于您的建筑项目。
for your construction projects.
作为回报，你想要吗？
And in return you want?
弗拉维安圆形剧场的财务参与。
Financial participation
in the Flavian Amphitheater.
这是一个奇怪的愿望。
(CHUCKLES)
That's a strange desire.
这没有利润。只有成本。
There's no profit in that.
Only costs.
目前。
For now.
做。
Done.
波尔图，把你最信任的人派到奥斯蒂亚，等待这个领航员。
Porto, post your
most trusted man in Ostia
to wait for this navigator.
他一到，就把他带到我面前。
Bring him before me
as soon as he arrives.
凯撒，你有我的感谢和忠诚。
You have my thanks,
and my loyalty, Caesar.
我只对后者感兴趣。你可以走了。
I'm only interested
in the latter. You may go.
我不得不说，兄弟，我看到你的目标更坚定了。
I have to say, brother,
I've seen you with steadier aim.
没有什么能让你感到不安。
Nothing used to unnerve you.
甚至连父亲的咳嗽都没有。
Not even Father's cough.
离开我们。
DOMITIAN: Leave us.
希腊人，他们说
Greeks, they say that
当宽恕之前有忏悔时，宽恕更容易给予。
forgiveness is easier to grant
when it's preceded
by confession.
你希望我坦白什么？
What do you wish me to confess?
莱托参议员告诉我
I'm told by Senator Leto
他的船务代理已经找到了证据
that his shipping agents
have found proof
你耽误了谷物。
that you delayed the grain.
但是兄弟，我不能承认我没有做过的事情。
But brother, I cannot confess
to something I didn't do.
显然，有一个证人
Apparently, there was a witness
在前往罗马的途中，他将证实一切。
en route to Rome
who will corroborate everything.
显然，涵盖了广泛的结果，
Apparently, covers
a wide range of outcomes,
而莱托是一个自私自利、野心勃勃的贵族，
and Leto is a self-serving,
ambitious patrician,
谁从一开始就憎恨我们的优越地位。
who's resented our ascendancy
from the start.
我知道这两件事。
I know both of these things.
然而，你却要我承认一些明显的不当行为。
And yet you asked me to confess
to some apparent misdeed.
差一点。
Not quite.
我正在向你学习如何玩这个游戏。
I'm learning how to play
this game from you.
所以我告诉你一个关于你的指责，
So I'm telling you
an accusation about you,
我在观察你的反应。
and I'm watching
how you respond.
你看到了什么？
And what do you see?
嗯，这是我仍在学习的部分。
Well, that's the part
I'm still learning.
我看到一个有点奇怪但忠诚的兄弟。
I see either a somewhat strange,
but loyal brother.
或者是我见过的最好的骗子。
Or the best liar
I have ever seen.
多莫斯。
Domus.
我想你会对我设计的节目感到满意。
I think you'll be pleased
with the show I've devised.
你辜负了我。
You have failed me.
你要掩盖我的踪迹，以防粮食延误。
You were to cover my tracks
for the grain delays.
一位来自运粮船的航海家幸存下来。
A navigator,
from a grain ship,
has survived.
他被带到罗马为提多作证。
He's been brought here to Rome
to testify to Titus.
然后我们杀了他。他对你们活着的人说的死话。
Then we kill him.
His dead words against
your living ones.
-他在哪？-为时已晚。
-Where is he?
-It's too late for that.
他已经作了书面证词。
He's already made
a written testimony.
剩下的就是让他和我哥哥确认一下。
All that's left is for him
to confirm it with my brother.
如果杀了他为时已晚，那又如何呢？
If it's too late to kill him,
then what?
我们杀了我的兄弟。
We kill my brother.
这一刻即将到来。要么杀人，要么被杀。
The moment is upon us.
Kill, or be killed.
好吧，我们可以在禁卫军中买谁？
All right, who among
the Praetorians can we buy?
爱马 仕。
Hermes.
图密善。
Domitian.
来吧，加入我们。
Come, join us.
抓住他。
Take him.
什么？不 不。
What? No, no.
图密善，拜托，拜托。我不明白。
Domitian, please, please.
I don't understand.
没有我的许可。
Not without my permission.
我很抱歉。
I'm so sorry.
对不起。对不起。不！
I'm sorry. I'm sorry. No!
请！
Please!
不，拜托！
No, please!
这里。这是他付给我的一切。
IRIS: Here. This is
everything he paid me.
皮条客：坐下。
PIMP: Sit down.
虹膜。跟我回家吧。
Iris. Come home with me.
你跟我来。
You're coming with me.
你去哪儿？
Where are you going?
她是我的财产，你这个婊子。
She's my property, you bitch.
如果你再靠近她，
If you go near her again,
我会慢慢杀了你。婊 子！
I will kill you slowly. Bitch!
鸢尾花，过来。
Iris, come.
-困扰？-你也是？
-Troubled?
-You as well?
我的女儿，奥拉。
My daughter, Aura.
她不再是我的了。
She is no longer mine.
我把她丢到了罗马。
I lost her to Rome.
你告诉我...
You told me...
对别人撒谎是可以的，但对自己撒谎是危险的。
that it's fine to lie to others,
but dangerous to lie
to yourself.
我把这句话记在心里。
I took that to heart.
你正在学习。
You're learning.
我可能不是你认为的那个。
I might not be quite the scum
you think I am.
而且我有可能是贵族血统。
And there is a chance
I am of patrician blood.
你们罗马人太愚蠢了。
You Romans are so foolish.
你认为血液很重要吗？
You think blood matters?
在罗马，鲜血就是一切。
In Rome, blood is everything.
有了正确的血液，一个人可以做任何事情。
With the right blood,
a man can do anything.
整个世界在他面前敞开。
The whole world
opens up before him.
你的新朋友，出身高贵的朋友，会忽略恶臭吗？
And will your new,
high-born friends,
ignore the stench
你去过哪里，你做了什么？
of where you've been
and what you've done?
他们忽略了更糟糕的情况。
They've ignored worse.
我不知道你是兴奋还是害怕。
I can't tell if you are
excited or frightened.
害怕。
Frightened.
我必须做一些可怕的事情。
I have to do something terrible.
这曾经给我带来快乐。
Which would have once
given me pleasure.
但是现在，如果我是一等罗马人，
But now, if I'm a Roman
of the first order,
这让我很害怕。
it terrifies me.
然后只想着快乐。
Then only think of the pleasure.
不。
No.
不。。。
Not...
不，什么？还没有？
No, what? Not yet?
我没这么说。
I didn't say that.
但你在想。
But you were thinking it.
也许。
Perhaps.
在萨姆尼亚，我有一个表弟。
In Samnia, I have a cousin.
他在地下的骨库工作。
He worked underground
in an ossuary.
从死者身上排出液体，
Draining fluids from the dead,
为地下室做准备。
preparing them for the crypts.
没有比这更低的了。
There is nothing lower.
他逃脱了。
He escaped that.
他自杀了？
He took his own life?
不，他是自愿入学的
No, he enrolled by free will
作为 Ludus Magnus 的角斗士。
as a gladiator
at the Ludus Magnus.
你是说他不是奴隶吗？
Do you mean he wasn't a slave?
许多人是奴隶。
Many are slaves.
但有些人是自愿来的。
But some come there by choice.
选择死在别人的手里。
Choosing death
by another's hand.
也许不是。
Maybe not.
三年过去了，他还活着。
It's been three years,
and he's still alive.
他有饭吃，有地方睡觉，受到尊重。
He eats,
he has a place to sleep,
and is treated with respect.
这不仅仅是男人。
It's not just men.
他们也招募女性作为角斗士。
They enlist women
as gladiators as well.
-女人？-人群觉得这很有趣。
-Women?
-The crowds find it amusing.
但有时候，一个女人打得那么好，
But sometimes,
a woman fights so well,
他们停止大笑。
that they stop laughing.
哇。
Whoa. (SHUSHES AND WHISTLES)
-嘿，简单，简单。
-Hey, easy, easy.
-(HORSE SNORTS)
煽动。
Incitatus.
你饿了吧？
You are hungry, huh? (CHUCKLES)
这里。
Here.
给你，男孩。
Here you go, boy.
在西班牙的家乡，我的祖父曾经说过，
Back home in Spain,
my grandfather used to say,
马是猎物，人是掠食者。
horses are prey,
and men are predators.
为了让一匹马奔跑，我们必须说服他们
To get a horse to run,
we must convince them
我们不是真正的我们。
that we are not
what we truly are.
杀手。
Killers.
首先，你让他们知道你不会伤害他们。
First, you let them know
that you are not
going to hurt them.
哇，嘘。但这还不够。
Whoa, shh.
But that is not enough.
让一匹马奔跑很容易。
To get a horse to run is easy.
为了让他真正飞起来，
To get him to really fly,
让他全心全意，
for him to give
his heart and soul,
汗水和肌肉，
and sweat and muscle,
我必须爱他。
I must love him.
他必须知道这一点。
And he must know it.
如果我以正确的方式告诉他，我有多爱他，
And if I tell him the right way,
how much I love him,
他会为我做任何事。
he will do anything for me.
你赌得很糟糕。
You made a bad bet.
我不知道。
I don't know.
也许提图斯不会再当皇帝了。
Perhaps Titus won't be Emperor
for much longer.
他身上有太多的士兵气质。
There's too much
of the soldier in him.
没有足够的政治家。
Not enough politician.
谁将取代他？
Who will supplant him?
图密善。答案是肯定的。
Domitian. Of course.
如果发生这种情况，
And if that were to happen,
所有忠于提多的人，都可能和他一起死。
all those loyal to Titus,
would likely die with him.
没有人喜欢松散的结局。
Nobody likes loose ends.
罗马曾有过像老人一样死去的战士统治者。
Rome has had warrior rulers
who died as old men.
也许在战时。
In wartime maybe.
但这是和平。危险得多。
But this is peace.
Far more dangerous.
在和平中，你不想要战士。
In peace,
you don't want warriors.
你想要街头霸王。
You want street fighters.
一千万塞斯特斯的黄金，两天后，
Ten million sesterces in gold,
two days from now,
在这个地方，
here in this place,
如果你试图讨价还价，
and if you try to bargain,
它只是告诉我图密善缺乏成功的资源，我会杀了你。
it merely tells me Domitian
lacks the resources to succeed,
and I will kill you.
并向提多报告他的叛国行为。
And report his treason to Titus.
两天。
Two days.
图密善比你想象的更接近死亡。
Domitian is closer to death
than you think.
如果他死了，他的朋友也会死。
And if he dies,
so will his friends.
没有人喜欢松散的结局。
Nobody likes loose ends.
京。
Ten million.
两天。
Two days.
哇，哇，哇。
ELIA: Whoa, whoa, whoa.
简单，简单。
Easy, easy.
耶！
Yah!
安德里亚！
Andria!
耶！
Yah!
您知道吗？他速度很快，非常快。
Did you know?
He's fast, very fast.